Duncan McArthur Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Duncan McArthur Papers 1783-1848
MSS31831
McArthur, Duncan, 1772-1839
4,600 items
54 containers
21.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Ohio governor and legislator, military officer, and U.S. representative. Correspondence, land survey notes, plats, tax returns, and other documents on land holdings in and near the Scioto River Valley in Ohio; also account books, orderly book of the U.S. 19th Infantry Regiment during the War of 1812, and printed matter. With the correspondence are army returns, reports, and general orders for the years 1814-1815 while McArthur was in command of the U.S. Army Department of the Northwest; other papers relate to the period of his congressional service.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
McArthur family.; McArthur, Duncan, 1772-1839.
Organizations
United States. Army. Department of the Northwest.; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 19th (1812-1815)
Subjects
Land tenure--Ohio.
Places
Ohio--Politics and government.; Scioto River Valley (Ohio)--History.; United States--History--War of 1812.; United States--Politics and government--1817-1825.
Occupations
Army officers.; Governors--Ohio.; Legislators--Ohio.; Representatives, U.S. Congress--Ohio.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Duncan McArthur, Ohio governor and legislator, military officer, and U.S. representative, were purchased by the Library of Congress in 1905.
Additional Guides
The Duncan McArthur Papers have been described in the Handbook of Manuscripts in the Library of Congress (Washington, 1918).
Transfers
Some printed matter has been transferred to the Library's Rare Book and Special Collections Division where it is identified as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Duncan McArthur are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1772, Jan. 14 Born, Dutchess County, N.Y.
1780 Moved to Pittsburgh, Pa.
1790 Participated in Josiah Harmar's campaign against the Shawnee Tribe of Native Americans and other expeditions
1792 1793 Worked as a salt-boiler near Maysville, Ky.
1793 Joined a party surveying under Nathaniel Massie from the Scioto River Valley to the area around Chillicothe, Ohio
circa 1893 1895 Observed the movement of Native Americans as a ranger
1795 Rejoined Nathaniel Massie and learned surveying
1796 Married Nancy McDonald and settled near Chillicothe, Ohio
1804 Elected to lower house, Ohio legislature
1805 1814 Member, Ohio state senate, speaker for the 1809-1810 session
1806 Elected a colonel in the Ohio militia
1808 Promoted to major-general
1812 Marched with Ohio militia for Detroit and later was elected colonel of one of the three militia regiments under the command of William Hull
1813 Brigadier general, Ohio Volunteers in defense of Fort Meigs
1814 Commanded troops at Sacketts Harbor on Lake Ontario and later appointed commander of the army in the Northwest
1815 1816 Member, lower house, Ohio state legislature
1816 Member of various commissions for treaty-making with Native Americans
1817 1818 Member, lower house, Ohio state legislature
1821 1823 Member, upper house, Ohio state legislature
1823 1825 Member, United States Congress
1829 1830 Member, upper house, Ohio state legislature
1830 1832 Governor of Ohio
1839, Apr. 28 Died at "Fruit Hill" near Chillicothe, Ohio
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Duncan McArthur (1772-1839) span the years 1783-1848 and consist of correspondence, land survey notes, plats, tax returns, and other documents on land holdings in and near the Scioto River Valley in Ohio; account books, orderly book of the United States 19th Infantry Regiment during the War of 1812, and printed matter. With the correspondence are army returns, reports, and general orders for the years 1814-1815 while McArthur was in command of the United States Army Department of the Northwest. Other papers relate to the period of his congressional service, 1823-1825. The collection also includes papers stemming from McArthur's daughters.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is organized into bound volumes arranged chronologically and unbound material by type of document or subject.
Container List
- Bound vols. (Box 1)
  - 1783, Oct. 5-1807, July 5 (Box 1)
  - 1807, July 5-1812, Dec. 2 (Box 2)
  - 1813, Dec. 3-1813, Sept. 20 (Box 3)
  - 1813, Sept. 22-1814, Feb. 2 (Box 4)
  - 1814 (Box 5)
    - Feb. 3-Mar. 1 (Box 5)
    - Mar. 2-30 (Box 6)
    - Mar. 31-Apr. 28 (Box 7)
    - Apr. 30-May 20 (Box 8)
    - May 21-June 8 (Box 9)
    - June 9-22 (Box 10)
    - June 23-July 2 (Box 11)
    - July 3-16 (Box 12)
    - July 17-Aug. 6 (Box 13)
    - Aug. 7-30 (Box 14)
    - Aug. 31-Sept. 15 (Box 15)
    - Sept. 16-29 (Box 16)
    - Sept. 30-Oct. 13 (Box 17)
    - Oct. 14-Nov. 2 (Box 18)
    - Nov. 3-24 (Box 19)
    - Nov. 25-Dec. 30 (Box 20)
    - 1814, Dec. 31-1815, Jan. 13 (Box 21)
  - 1815 (Box 22)
    - Jan. 14-Feb. 1 (Box 22)
    - Feb. 2-Mar. 2 (Box 23)
    - Mar. 3-30 (Box 24)
    - Mar. 31-May 15 (Box 25)
    - May 26-July 10 (Box 26)
  - 1815, July 12-1817, Jan. 30 (Box 27)
  - 1817, Feb. 1-1818, Nov. 24 (Box 28)
  - 1818, Nov. 26-1821, Feb. 9 (Box 29)
  - 1821, Feb. 13-1822, Nov. 5 (Box 30)
  - 1822, Nov. 6-1824, Feb. 23 (Box 31)
  - 1824, Feb. 24-Dec. 21 (Box 32)
  - 1824, Dec. 22-1825, Aug. 31 (Box 33)
  - 1825, Sept. 1-1826, June 14 (Box 34)
  - 1826, June 15-1827, Jan. 19 (Box 35)
  - 1827, Jan. 20-1827, July 29 (Box 36)
  - 1827, July 30-1828, June 15 (Box 37)
  - 1828, June 17-1829, June 3 (Box 38)
  - 1829, June 4-1830, Feb. 6 (Box 39)
  - 1830, Feb. 7-Sept. 23 (Box 40)
  - 1830, Sept. 25-1831, Mar. 14 (Box 41)
  - 1831, Mar. 16-1832, Feb. 1 (Box 42)
  - 1832, Feb. 3-1832, Nov. 5 (Box 43)
  - 1834, Nov. 6-1834, Mar. 7 (Box 44)
  - 1834, Mar. 8-1835, May 9 (Box 45)
  - 1835, May 11-1848, June 4 (Box 46)
  - Undated (Box 47)
  - Undated (Box 48)
  - Account books (Box 49)
    - 1809-1811 (Box 49)
    - 1814-1815 (Box 50)
- Unbound material (Box 51)
  - Almanac, circa 1779-1780, (1 vol.) (Box 51)
  - Financial papers (Box 51)
    - Account books, 1824-1837, undated, (4 vols.) (Box 51)
    - Checks, receipts, etc., (2 folders) (Box 51)
  - "Indian treaties," 1817 (Box 51)
  - Land documents, (2 folders); (5 folders); (4 folders) (Box 51, Box 52, Box 53, Box 54)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 54)
  - Ohio general assembly, a bill for organizing and disciplining the militia, circa 1825 (Box 54)
  - Orderly book, United States 19th Infantry Regiment, 1812-1813 (Box 54)